<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD RFC 2629//EN" "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-ssh-hostname-extension-01" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" consensus="true" updates="4252">
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc strict="yes" ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes"?>
  <?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SSH VHost extension">
        Accessing a Virtual Host over SSH
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" status="experimental" value="draft-ietf-ssh-hostname-extension-01"/>
    <seriesInfo name="ISSN" value="2070-1721"/>
    <author fullname="Rolf van Kleef" initials="R. H. B." role="editor" surname="van Kleef">
      <organization>Individual Contributor</organization>
      <address>
        <email>rfc@rolfvankleef.nl</email>
        <uri>https://rolfvankleef.nl/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <area>int</area>
    <area>tsv</area>
    <keyword>SSH</keyword>
    <keyword>HOST</keyword>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document describes an extension for SSH that allows an SSH server
        to identify which virtual host a client is attempting to connect to.
        It ensures that unextended clients can interoperate with extended
        servers and vice-versa, albeit without the features provided as a
        result of this document.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
        Many application-layer protocols already have means of specifying which
        "virtual host" a client intends to connects to.
        Examples are the HTTP 'Host' header as specified by
        <xref target="IANA_MH">the IANA Message Headers</xref> list, and the
        <xref target="RFC7151">FTP HOST command</xref>.
        Most of these implementations note that it is used to identify different
        virtual hosts where multiple DNS names resolve to one IP address.
        The goal of this document is to make it possible to implement similar
        features to SSH by enhancing the 'username' field in the user
        authentication packet so that it can be used to specify to which
        virtual host the client means to connect.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      <t>
        The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
        "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in
        <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Throughout this document, when the fields are referenced, they will
        appear within single quotes.
        When values to fill those fields are referenced, they will appear
        within double quotes.
        Using the above example, possible values for 'data' are "foo" and
        "bar".
      </t>
      <t>
        The required syntax is defined using the Augmented BNF defined in
        <xref target="RFC5243"/>. 
        Some general ABNF definitions are required throughout the document;
        they will be defined in subsequent sections.
      </t>
      <t>
        With the increased use of virtualization technologies, there may be
        several possible definitions for the term "virtual host".
        This document follows the definition from
        <xref target="RFC3875" section="4.1.14" sectionFormat="of"/>, where
        several virtual hosts share the same IP address, and hostnames are used
        by the server-SSH process to route sessions to the appropriate virtual
        host.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Updates for SSH_MSG_USERAUTH_REQUEST">
      <t>
        This document proposes the name of the virtual host be placed in the
        'username' field of the <tt>SSH_MSG_USERAUTH_REQUEST</tt> message
        next to the actual username.
      </t>
      <section title="Syntax of the 'username' Field">
        <t>
          The method of embedding the name of the virtual host in the
          'username' field of the aforementioned packet is separating the
          username and the name of the virtual host by an "@"-sign.
          The name of the virtual host <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid
          hostname as specified by
          <xref target="RFC3986" section="3.2.2" sectionFormat="of"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          It should still be possible to simply specify a username without a
          specification of a virtual host.
          If this is wanted, an "@"-sign <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be appended to the
          username, unless the username does not contain an "@"-sign, in which
          case, an "@"-sign <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be appended to the
          username.
        </t>
        <t>
          Formalizing the preceding text, the value of the 'username' field
          of the <tt>SSH_MSG_USERAUTH_REQUEST</tt> will conform to this
          grammar:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>'username' field grammar</name>
          <sourcecode type="abnf" name="'username' field grammar">
username_value    =  username "@" virtual_host_name
username_value    =/ username "@"
username_value    =/ username_noat

username          =  1*(%x01-%x10FFFF)
username_noat     =  1*(%x01-%x39 / %x41-%x10FFFF)
virtual_host_name =  &lt;See section 3.2.2 of RFC3986&gt;</sourcecode>
        </figure>
        <t>
          When this grammar, with the root symbol of 'username_value' is used
          to parse the 'username' field, the value of the symbol 'username'
          or 'username_noat' are to be used as if they are the username, and
          the value of the symbol 'virtual_host_name' may be used as the name
          of the virtual host, if it is present.
          If the symbol 'virtual_host_name' is absent, no virtual host name is
          specified.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examples">
        <table>
          <name>Examples of values in the 'username' field</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Transmitted string</th>
              <th>Actual username</th>
              <th>Actual host</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user@host.example</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>host.example</tt></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user@@host.example</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user@</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>host.example</tt></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user</tt></td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user@name@host.example</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user@name</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>host.example</tt></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user@x@@</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user@x@</tt></td>
              <td/>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <tt>user@[ff::ff]</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>user</tt></td>
              <td>
                <tt>[ff::ff]</tt></td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Interoperability">
      <t>
        It is essential that older implementations of SSH servers and clients
        will keep working, even when the other party does support the protocol
        alterations as described in this document.
        It is acceptable to fall back to the behaviour and featureset of the
        SSH protocol without the features and behaviours resulting from the
        extension described in this document.
        In order to do this, this document describes an extension which can be
        either present or absent.
        In order to communicate to the other party whether this extension is
        supported, the negotiation protocol as described in
        <xref target="RFC8308"/> is used with the extension name as discussed
        in <xref target="iana_additions"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        When a new client is used to connect to a server that does not support
        the extension described in this document, the client
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> submit a name of the virtual host and
        <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> append the username with an "@"-sign.
        Any services that depend on the specification of a virtual host can
        be expected to be absent or dysfunctional, and should not be
        requested.
      </t>
      <t>
        When the server detects a client that does not support the
        extension described in this document, the server
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> interpret the username field as if it is a username
        in its entirity, without attempting to split out a hostname.
        The server should then proceed as if no virtual host was specified by
        the client.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="iana_additions" title="Additions to Existing Registries">
        <t>
          Under the "Secure Shell (SSH) Protocol Parameters, Extension Names"
          registry as defined in
          <xref target="RFC8308" section="4.2" sectionFormat="of"/>,
          IANA is requested to assign the proposed extension name 'virtualhost'
          to be used as described in this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        All the credentials are submitted over a secure line.
        That means that the name of the virtual host is submitted over a secure
        transport as well.
        The extension information is not submitted over a secure line.
        It is, in fact, submitted over plaintext.
        That means that a potential attacker could override advertised support,
        or lack thereof, of the extension described in this document.
        This does not introduce a critical security issue, as overriding
        this will very likely cause a failed authentication, either because
        the requested user does not exist on the server, or because the
        credentials used are not valid for the requested user.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <reference anchor="RFC2119" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
        <front>
          <title>Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate Requirement Levels</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Bradner" fullname="S. Bradner">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="1997" month="March"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>In many standards track documents several words are used to signify the requirements in the specification.  These words are often capitalized. This document defines these words as they should be interpreted in IETF documents.  This document specifies an Internet Best Current Practices for the Internet Community, and requests discussion and suggestions for improvements.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="BCP" value="14"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="2119"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC2119"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3875" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3875" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3875.xml">
        <front>
          <title>The Common Gateway Interface (CGI) Version 1.1</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Robinson" fullname="D. Robinson">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="K." surname="Coar" fullname="K. Coar">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2004" month="October"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>The Common Gateway Interface (CGI) is a simple interface for running external programs, software or gateways under an information server in a platform-independent manner.  Currently, the supported information servers are HTTP servers. </t>
            <t> The interface has been in use by the World-Wide Web (WWW) since 1993.  This specification defines the 'current practice' parameters of the 'CGI/1.1' interface developed and documented at the U.S. National Centre for Supercomputing Applications.  This document also defines the use of the CGI/1.1 interface on UNIX(R) and other, similar systems.  This memo provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3875"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3875"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC3986" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3986" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
        <front>
          <title>Uniform Resource Identifier (URI): Generic Syntax</title>
          <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="T. Berners-Lee">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="Fielding" fullname="R. Fielding">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="L." surname="Masinter" fullname="L. Masinter">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2005" month="January"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>A Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) is a compact sequence of characters that identifies an abstract or physical resource.  This specification defines the generic URI syntax and a process for resolving URI references that might be in relative form, along with guidelines and security considerations for the use of URIs on the Internet.  The URI syntax defines a grammar that is a superset of all valid URIs, allowing an implementation to parse the common components of a URI reference without knowing the scheme-specific requirements of every possible identifier.  This specification does not define a generative grammar for URIs; that task is performed by the individual specifications of each URI scheme.  [STANDARDS-TRACK]</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="STD" value="66"/>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3986"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3986"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC5243" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5243" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5243.xml">
        <front>
          <title>OSPF Database Exchange Summary List Optimization</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Ogier" fullname="R. Ogier">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2008" month="May"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a backward-compatible optimization for the Database Exchange process in OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.  In this optimization, a router does not list a Link State Advertisement (LSA) in Database Description packets sent to a neighbor, if the same or a more recent instance of the LSA was listed in a Database Description packet already received from the neighbor.  This optimization reduces Database Description overhead by about 50% in large networks.  This optimization does not affect synchronization, since it only omits unnecessary information from Database Description packets.  This memo  provides information for the Internet community.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="5243"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC5243"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC7151" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7151" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7151.xml">
        <front>
          <title>File Transfer Protocol HOST Command for Virtual Hosts</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Hethmon" fullname="P. Hethmon">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <author initials="R." surname="McMurray" fullname="R. McMurray">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2014" month="March"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>The File Transfer Protocol, as defined in RFC 959, does not provide a way for FTP clients and servers to differentiate between multiple DNS names that are registered for a single IP address.  This document defines a new FTP command that provides a mechanism for FTP clients and servers to identify individual virtual hosts on an FTP server.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="7151"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC7151"/>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="RFC8308" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8308" xml:base="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8308.xml">
        <front>
          <title>Extension Negotiation in the Secure Shell (SSH) Protocol</title>
          <author initials="D." surname="Bider" fullname="D. Bider">
            <organization/>
          </author>
          <date year="2018" month="March"/>
          <abstract>
            <t>This memo updates RFCs 4251, 4252, 4253, and 4254 by defining a mechanism for Secure Shell (SSH) clients and servers to exchange information about supported protocol extensions confidentially after SSH key exchange.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8308"/>
        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8308"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="IANA_MH" target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/message-headers/message-headers.xhtml">
        <front>
          <title>IANA Message Header registry</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Internet Assigned Numbers Authority</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!-- vim: ts=2:sts=2:sw=2:expandtab
-->
